现在我们理解了安全PRG和语义安全
So now that we understand what a secure
PRG is, and we understand what semantic
我们可以证明用安全PRG的流密码
security means, we can actually argue that
a stream cipher with a secure PRG is, in
事实上是语义安全的
这是我们本节的目标
fact, semantically secure. So that's our
goal for this, segment. It's a fairly
这是一个很直接的证明，我们会看到怎么做
我们要证明的理论是
straightforward proof, and we'll see how
it goes. So the theory we wanna prove is
给一个安全的发生器G，伪随机发生器
that, basically, given a generator G that
happens to be a secured, pseudo-random
事实上，由这个发生器推出的流密码
generator. In fact, the stream cipher
that's derived from this generator is
将是语义安全的，需要强调
going to be semantically secure. Okay and
I want to emphasize. That there was no
对完美安全，不存在这样的定理
hope of proving a theorem like this for
perfect secrecy. For Shannons concept of
对香农的完美安全，因为我们知道
流密码不可能是完美安全的
perfect secrecy. Because we know that a
stream cipher can not be perfectly
因为它的密钥太短，同时
完美安全要求密钥至少
secure because it has short keys. And
perfect secrecy requires the keys to be as
和明文一样长。那么这是第一个例子
long as the message. So this is really
kind of the first example the we see where
我们看到，可以证明短密钥的密码
也有安全性，即语义安全的概念
we're able to prove that a cipher with
short keys has security. The concept of
这里将证实，这是个非常有用的概念
security is semantic security. And this
actually validates that, really, this is a
事实上，我们将使用语义安全
very useful concept. And in fact, you
know, we'll be using semantic security
很多很多次，贯穿于本课程中。
好，那我们如何证明这么个定理呢？
many, many times throughout the course.
Okay, so how do we prove a theory like
方法是，证明它的逆否命题
this? What we're actually gonna be doing,
is we're gonna be proving the
我们如下进行证明
contrapositive. What we're gonna show is
the following. So we're gonna prove this
我们要证这个命题，让我为大家解读一下
假设有一威胁语义安全的攻击者A
statement down here, but let me parse it
for you. Suppose. You give me a semantic
我们将构造一个PRG攻击者B
security adversary A. What we'll do is
we'll build PRG adversary B to satisfy
以满足这个不等式。
为什么这个不等式有用呢？
this inequality here. Now why is this
inequality useful? Basically what do we
我们知道什么？我们知道如果B
是个有效攻击者，那么
know? We know that if B is an efficient
adversary. Then we know that since G is a
由于发生器G是安全的，我们知道
这个优势是可以忽略的，对吧？
secure generator, we know that this
advantage is negligible, right? A secure
一个安全的发生器对一切有效统计测试
都有可忽略的优势
generator has a negligible advantage
against any efficient statistical test. So
所以右边是可忽略的，不过
the right hand side, basically, is gonna
be negligible. But because the right hand
因为右边是可忽略的，我们可以推出
左边也是可忽略的
side is negligible, we can deduce that the
left hand side is negligible.
所以大家看到的攻击者
在攻击流密码E时
And therefore, the adversary that you looked
at actually has negligible advantage in
只有可忽略的优势。好
这就是其中的道理
attacking the stream cipher E. Okay. So
this is how this, this will work.
对任一攻击者A，我们都能构造出
Basically all we have to do is given an
adversary A we're going to build an
一个攻击者B。我们知道攻击者B
对发生器只有可忽略的优势
adversary B. We know that B has negligible
advantage against generator but that
这就意味着A对流密码的优势也是可忽略的
implies that A has negligible advantage against the stream cipher.
(更自然地，若A优势不可忽略，则我们能
构造出B来破解PRG，即PRG不安全)
这么做。给定A，我们只要构造B
So let's do that. So all we have to do again
is given A, we have to build B.
设A为一威胁流密码语义安全的攻击者
So let A be a semantic security adversary against
the stream cipher. So let me remind you
提示一下，这意味着有一挑战者
what that means. Basically, there's a
challenger. The challenger starts off by
挑战者选择密钥K，然后攻击者输出两个明文
choosing the key K. And then the adversary
is gonna output two messages, two equal
两个等长的明文M0和M1。
他将收到M0或M1的加密结果
length messages. And he's gonna receive
the encryption of M0 or M1
并输出B1。好，这就是这个攻击者的所做
and outputs B1. Okay, that's
what a semantic security adversary is
那么现在我们开始和这个攻击者玩这个游戏
going to do. So now we're going to start
playing games with this adversary. And
这就是证明我们的引理的方法
that's how we're going to prove our
lemma. Alright, so the first thing
好，我们第一件事是让挑战者选择随机字符串R
we're going to do is we're going to make
the challenger. Also choose a random R.
好，随机字符串R。攻击者并不关心
Okay, a random string R. So, well you know
the adversary doesn't really care what the
挑战者里面是怎么做的。
挑战者不使用R，所以这不影响
challenger does internally. The challenger
never uses R, so this doesn't affect the
攻击者的优势。攻击者也不在乎
adversary's advantage at all. The
adversary just doesn't care that the
挑战者也选取了R。这里有个技巧
challenger also picks R. But now comes the
trick. What we're going to do is we're
我们不使用密钥K加密，而是使用R加密
going to, instead of encrypting using key K.
We're going to encrypt using R. You can
可以看到我们是这样做的
see basically what we're doing
here. Essentially we're changing the
我们改变了挑战者，现在挑战者输出的
密文是用一纯随机密码本加密的
challenger so now the challenge
cipher text is encrypted using a
不使用伪随机密码本GK
truly random pad. As opposed to just pseudo
random pad GK. Okay. Now, the property of
这个伪随机数发生器(PRG)的性质是
它的输出与真随机不可区分
the pseudo-random generator is that its
output is indistinguishable from truly
因为这个PRG是安全的，攻击者无法分别
random. So, because the PRG is secure, the
adversary can't tell that we made this
其中的不同。攻击者不能判断
我们是否从伪随机字符串切换到了
change. The adversary can't tell that we
switched from a pseudo-random string to a
真随机字符串了。这又是因为
这个发生器是安全的
truly random string. Again, because the
generator is secure. Well, but now look at
但是现在看我们得到的这个游戏。
攻击者的优势不会改变很多
the game that we ended up with. So the
adversary's advantage couldn't have
因为他不能区分其中的不同，
不过看我们的这个游戏
changed by much, because he can't tell the
difference. But now look at the game that
这个游戏是一个一次性密码本的游戏
we ended up with. Now this game is truly a
one time pad game. This a semantic
这是个一次性密码本语义安全的游戏
因为现在攻击者获得了
security game against the one time pad.
Because now the adversary is getting a one
M0和M1的一次性密码本的加密结果
在一次性密码本中
time pad encryption of M0 or M1. But in the
one time pad we know that the adversaries
优势为0，因为一次性密码本无法破解
advantage is zero, because you can't beat
the one time pad. The one time pad is
一次性密码本是无条件地安全的，因此
secure. Unconditionally secure. And as a
result, because of this. Essentially
攻击者不能说出
because the adversary couldn't have told
the difference when
这里伪随机和真随机的不同。他不能赢
we moved from pseudo random to random.
But he couldn't win the random game.
That also means that he
这也意味着他不能赢下这个伪随机游戏
因此，这个流密码
couldn't win the pseudo random game. And as
a result, the stream cipher, the original
最初的流密码一定是安全的
那就是证明的直观思路
stream cipher must be secure. So that's
the intuition for how the proof is gonna go.
我想再严格地证一遍。现在开始
But I wanna do it rigorously once.
From now on, we're just gonna argue by
我们与挑战者进行游戏
我们今后不会这么形式化
playing games with our challenger. And, we
won't be doing things as formal as I'm
但这一次，我想要精确地、形式化地证明
gonna do next. But I wanna do formally and
precisely once, just so that you see how
这样大家可以看到这些证明的原理
我先引入一些记号
these proofs actually work. Okay, so I'm
gonna have to introduce some notation. And
我用最常见的记号
如果这里最初的语义
I'll do the usual notation, basically. If
the original semantics are here at the
当我们使用伪随机密码本时
我将使用W0和W1
beginning, when we're actually using a
pseudo-random pad, I'm gonna use W0 and W1
来表示攻击者输出1的事件
to denote the event that the adversary
outputs one, when it gets the encryption
在分别加密M0或M1的情况下，好吧？
of M0, or gets the encryption of M1,
respectively. Okay? So W0 corresponds to
W0对应收到M0的密文，输出1
outputting 1 when receiving the
encryption of M0. And W1 corresponds
W1对应收到M1的密文，输出1
to outputting 1 when receiving the
encryption of M1. So that's the standard
这是语义安全的标准定义
现在我们换到随机密码本
definition of semantic security. Now once
we flip to the random pad. I'm gonna use
我用R0和R1来表示攻击者输出1
R0 and R1 to denote the event that the
adversary outputs 1 when receiving the
在分别加密M0或M1的情况下
one-time pad encryption of M0 or the
one-time pad encryption of M1. So we have
所以我们有4个事件: W0，W1
是来自原语义安全游戏的
four events, W0, W1 from the original
semmantics security game, and R0 and R1
R0, R1是来自换成一次性密码本的
语义安全游戏
from the semmantics security game once we
switch over to the one-time pad. So now
现在我们看这些变量间的关系
首先，R0和R1是来自
let's look at relations between these
variables. So first of all, R0 and R1 are
换成一次性密码本的语义安全游戏
basically events from a semmantics
security game against a one-time pad. So
我们说了，这些概率间的区别
the difference between these probabilities
is that, as we said, basically the
就是攻击者A的算法的优势
对一次性密码本的
advantage of algorithm A, of adversary A,
against the one-time pad. Which we know is
我们知道优势是0。很好
那就意味着R0的概率等于
zero. Okay, so that's great. So that
basically means that probability of, of R0
R1的概率。现在，我们把这些事件
放在一条线上
is equal to the probability of R1. So now,
let's put these events on a line, on a
这条线将0和1分开.这些是事件
W0和W1是我们感兴趣的事件
line segment between zero and one. So here
are the events. W0 and W1 are the events
我们想证明这俩很接近。好
we're interested in. We wanna show that
these two are close. Okay. And the way
方法是。。。哦，应该说
we're going to do it is basically by
showing, oh and I should say, here is
这是R0和R1的概率，它们一样
我把它们放在一起
probability R0 and R1, it says
they're both same, I just put them in the
我们要证明W0和W1
same place. What we're gonna do is we're
gonna show that both W0 and W1 are
实际上很接近Rb的概率
从而它们彼此也很接近
actually close to the probability of RB
and as a result they must be close to one
好，我们使用第二个论断
another. Okay, so the way we do that is
using a second claim, so now we're
我们对Wb和Rb间的距离感兴趣
interested in the distance between
probability of Wb and the probability of
好，那我待会要证明这个论断
我先表达这个论断
Rb. Okay so we'll prove the claim in a
second. Let me just state the claim. The
这个论断是说，存在攻击者B
使得这两个概率的差别
claim says that there exists an adversary
B. Such that the difference of these two
就是B对发生器G的优势
probabilities is basically the advantage
of B against the generator G and this is
这对两个b都成立，好吧？
给了这两个论断，定理就证毕了
for both b's. Okay? So given these two
claims, like the theorem is done because
因为我们知道这个距离比B对G的优势小
basically what do we know. We know this
distance is less than the advantage of B
那是根据第二个论断的
类似地，这个距离其实
against G. That's from claim two and
similarly, this distance actually is even
甚至等于B对G的优势，
而不是小于它
equal to, I'm not gonna say
less but is equal to the advantage. Of B
因此你可以看到W0和W1的距离
against G, and as a result you can see
that the distance between W0 and W1
最多是B对G的优势的两倍
is basically at most twice the
advantage of B against G. That's basically
这是我们要证明的论断
好的，剩下的工作就是
the thing that we are trying to prove.
Okay the only thing that remains is just
证明论断2。如果你想知道论断2的内容
proving this claim two and if you think
about what claim two says, it basically
它抓住了实验0中发生的
captures the question of what happens in
experiment zero what happens when we
当我们用真随机R替换伪随机密码本GK
所发生的问题
replace the pseudo random pad GK, by
truly random pad R. Here in
在这个实验0中，我们使用伪随机密码本
experiment zero say we're using the pseudo
random pad and here in experiment zero we
在这个实验0中，我们使用真随机密码本
我们问攻击者是否能
are using a Truly random pad and we are
asking can the adversary tell the
知道两者的差别。我们说，他不能
difference between these two and we wanna
argue that he cannot because the generator
因为发生器是安全的。好了
这就是我们要做的，来证明论断2
is secure. Okay so here's what we are
gonna do. So let's prove claim two. So we
我们说，事实上有一PRG攻击者B
are gonna argue that in fact there is a
PRG adversary B that has exactly the
他的优势严格地为两概率的差
difference of the two probabilities as
it's advantage. Okay and since the point
好，因为这是可忽略的
is since this is negligible this is
negligible. And that's basically what we
是我们想证明的。好
我们看统计测试b
wanted to prove. Okay, so let's look at
the statistical test b. So, what, our
我们的统计测试b将在内部使用攻击者A
statistical test b is gonna use adversary
A in his belly, so we get to build
所以我们按需要构建统计测试b
我们说了，内部使用攻击者A
statistical test b however we want. As we
said, it's gonna use adversary A inside of
这是个常规的统计测试
以n位字符串为输入
it, for its operation, and it's a regular
statistical test, so it takes an n-bit
它要输出判断，随机或不随机
string as inputs, and it's supposed to
output, you know, random or non-random,
0或1。好，我们看看它做的第一件事
zero or one. Okay, so let's see. So it's,
first thing it's gonna do, is it's gonna
运行攻击者A，攻击者A输出两个信息M0和M1
run adversary A, and adversary A is gonna
output two messages, M0 and M1. And then,
然后攻击者b回应
用M0异或输入的字符串
what adversary b's gonna do, is basically
gonna respond with M0 XOR the string that
对吧？然后这是统计测试了
it was given as inputs. Alright? That's
the statistical test, then. Whenever A
无论何时A输出，它就会原封不动地输出
同样结果。现在我们看它的优势
outputs, it's gonna output, its output.
And now let's look at its advantage. So
对这个发生器，这个统计测试的优势
what can we say about the advantage of
this statistical test against the
是多少？根据定义
如果你选择一个真随机字符串
generator? Well, so by definition, it's
the probability that, if you choose a
这里是^n
truly random string. So here are 01
to the N, so probability
答案就是B输出1的概率，减去
that R, that B outputs 1 minus the
probability, is that when we choose a
当我们选择伪随机字符串时，
B输出1的概率，对吧？
pseudo random string, B outputs 1, okay?
Okay, but let's think about what this is.
想一想，前面的表达式说明什么？
What can you tell me about the first
expressions? What can you tell me about
这里的表达式说明什么？根据定义
想想这里发生的
this expression over here? Well, by the
definition that's exactly if you think
那严格地是R0的概率，对吧？
about what's going on here, that's this is
exactly the probability R0 right?
因为我们与攻击者玩的这个游戏
Because this game that we are playing with
the adversary here is basically he outputed
这里攻击者输出M0和M1
M0 and M1 right here he outputed
M0 and M1 and he got the encryption
他获得了真随机一次密码本加密的M0
好，这是一个概率
of M0 under truly one time pad. Okay,
so this is basically a probability. Here
让我写得更好一些
那是R0的概率
let me write this a little better. That's
the basically the probability of R0.
那下一个表达式什么意思？
Now, what can we say about the next
expression, well what can we say about
当给B输入伪随机字符串Y时
when B is given a pseudo random
string Y as input.
这时，这是实验0和真流密码的游戏
Well in that case, this is exactly
experiment zero and true stream cipher game
因为现在我们要计算M异或M0，异或GK
这严格地为W0
because now we're computing M XOR M0,
XOR GK. This is exactly W0.
好，那正是我们要证明的
这个证明很简单
Okay, that's exactly what we have to prove.
So it's kind of a trivial proof.
好，这就完成了论断2的证明
为确保都讲清楚了
Okay, so that completes the proof of claim two.
And again, just to make sure this is all clear, once we have
我们一旦有了论断2，我们知道W0一定
和W1很接近，即为定理
claim two, we know that W0 must be close
to W1, and that's the theorem.
证毕！好现在我们已经建立了
一个事实上语义安全的流密码
That's what we have to prove. Okay, so now we've
established that a stream cypher is in
假定它的PRG是安全的
fact symmantically secure, assuming that
the PRG is secure.
【伊卡酱 译注】